Good morning,
everyone, and welcome back to
Ello Unsupervised 2026.
This morning
we are going to go ahead and get started
with our first workshop of the day
in the Algorithms and Imaginaries track.
So welcome Samya
and Shanmugapriya for the workshop
publishing Electronic Literature Research
in Metric driven Academia A roadmap
for Electronic Literature scholars.
And I'll turn it over to you all.
Yep. Thank you so much.
I'll just lay out
the ambit of the conference.
Then you can take it away.
And wherever you want me to come in, I'll.
I'll come in and say and contribute,
however.
Yeah.
So let's begin.
Okay.
So this is first.
First things first
I would like to acknowledge
our co conspirator of this event,
Shanmugam
Priya
who is preoccupied who could not make it.
But I'm sure she is here with us
in spirits and with all of her energies,
no matter wherever she is occupied.
She has been a very fundamental part
of all of our planning and conspiracies in
in whatever we do in electronic
literature, in and around India, wherever.
So I just want to give her a shout out.
So this is the third
or fourth, probably
the third iteration of this workshop that
I am doing in collaboration
with people ladders.
The first one happened at the New Media
Writing prize is unconference in 2024.
It was followed up by 2024.
By the likes of yourselves.
Once again, I'm very grateful
to have been joined by my brother
Coconspirator Mehul decide
who is a PhD scholar from it.
He is working under the supervision
of Shanmugam
Priya
keeping things in the family as we said.
So let's quickly move forward
and I will move my brains to major.
So please take it away and floor is yours.
Wherever you want me to come
in, I can come in and then we will engage
in more discussions.
I think that would be more fruitful.
Thank you. Thank you.
Hello everyone.
I am and I am a scholar
at Alien Institute of Technology,
Indian School of Mines in India.
My research work is situated
at the intersection
of electronic literature,
interactive digital
narratives, digital humanities
and the creative industries.
My research examines how one digital
literary forms, narrative interactivity
and computational creativity,
contemporary cultural production
with particular attention
to emergent practices in South.
I am also affiliated researcher
at Electronic Literature Lab at what?
Central State University, Vancouver.
I must thank Samya
and for giving me the opportunity
and making a part of this wonderful.
Next slide please.
Hello?
Yeah.
So here is the visual representation
of how
we search when we search in scholar.
What is electronic literature.
So when any scholar tries
like the first one on the left
is the visual representation of by Samia,
which he presented
in the last
in the previous workshop during 2024.
And this is the the on the right side
there is a visual representation
which I captured yesterday.
So as you can see,
the results are the same.
Even after two years nothing has changed.
The same books,
the same publications are there.
So we.
Show some really like to elaborate here.
Sorry. Could you repeat?
Your connection is breaking a little bit.
Oh. I'm sorry.
Would you like to elaborate here?
Your experience?
Yeah.
Are you breaking or is really audible?
And it is my connection that is unstable.
No, it's not just you.
Yeah. Okay, fine.
So I will just take a cue from
Mahle, and I will give a few indications
about about this thing.
So what we are trying to do here is
we are trying to gather a snapshot
of the publication spectrum of electronic
literature across the field.
Is that when we enter the keyword of
electronic literature in Google Scholar,
what are the things that show up?
Of course, Scott Redbirds book.
Get Katherine Hill's book
and Leo Flores articles.
These are very, very important,
and these are foundational
scholarships in the field.
There is absolutely no doubt about them.
But there is one particular problem.
The problem is that who of the very,
very important works here are monographs.
Now, monographs can only be written
by scholars, professors, practitioners
when they achieve
a level of critical mass via
which they can, they can write a monograph
in the first place.
And Leo Flores, my own supervisors
work is in the Electronic Book Review,
which later got published, I think,
as a part of the Bloomsbury Collection
that came out in 2021
or something like that.
I might be very wrong,
but there is a fundamental problem,
and that in this particular problem
is where our workshop begins,
is that the field of electronic literature
is very up and coming in, in in
a country like India,
there are a lot of people
who are interested in pursuing research
in this field, especially doing their PhDs
and graduating
and then coming into the job market,
digital humanities, electronic literature,
things like that.
But the problem is that
if they need to graduate their PhDs
and pass their defenses and get it in your
or whatever, we understand, but in it
position in in
this country and beyond or go elsewhere,
they need a very specific thing
called publications in indexed journals.
And these index journals can mean Web
of Science, Scopus and things like that.
Why I absolutely resist
these systems of power
because they are systems of power,
and they try to standardize
what publications mean for us,
which should not be the case.
But at the same time,
it is also important for us
to make pathways for scholars
who can publish in these types of journals
so that their work is recognized. With
the wider academia,
they can get avenues of publication,
and their work is recognized
so that they can create pathways
to break these forms of power
and move on in their careers.
So this is
this is a kind of stepping stone
to establish scholars
like myself, like me, who can have
avenues of publication
and of of registering their scholarship
in the broader domain for which
they get mileage in their workspace.
It is a very material construction,
and I'm being very deliberately
provocative in my argument.
Could you
could you talk about a little bit? Okay.
I'll just give
a little bit of a background.
So if I look into some of these
very, very important
and seminal publications, is,
is electronic literature
as world literature
or the universality of writing,
which comes from the extremely prestigious
poetics today, sports
work comes in Digital Humanities
Quarterly.
Most work comes in digital scholarship
in the humanities.
And this special issue done
by Mark comes from CLC web.
Now, the reason why
I display some journal publications here
is that there is a problem.
When we approach journals like Poetics
Today, Comparative Literature and Culture.
The problem is that unless
and until you know already
how to speak their language or how exactly
you can address their concerns
for you, very honest.
You have a lot of time
to hone your scholarship with that
journal across
reviews and edits and peer reviews.
It is not at all easy
to publish in these avenues, especially
the ones that conform to traditional
understanding of literary studies.
Digital humanities
journals like DSH and DK
are some of the most recognized journals.
But as everybody wants to publish
in these journals, it takes a lot of time
to publish Indian journals,
which graduate students often
don't have because they are chasing
a timeline to graduate.
So these are some of our experiences.
I myself have published
in Electronic Book Review and with Astrid
in a very prestigious journal
from classical.
But even after having.
Outputs, I will still ask.
We will not let you progress that
that you have to have
certain kinds of publication.
It's like Orwell ending Animal Farm,
that all publications are equal,
but some publications are more equal
than other publications.
Right.
And these are some of works.
Of course I will I.
Yes, please. Please. I'm sorry.
Thank you, thank you.
So to bring in Doctor
Shannon has experience.
She was among the first scholars in India
to begin working on electronically.
Twitter.
She has mentioned it
in one of our discussions
that when she was in her PhD,
she was not fully aware
of the importance of importance
attached to index journals.
Publications.
She wrote some of the foundational.
Sorry. Yeah.
C c wrote
some of the foundational papers on
Indian electronic
literature and published them in non
indexed journals.
Her only paper, published in an index
to Journal appeared in DSH is highlighted.
However, the foundational papers
she published in non indexed journals
did not get counted in
in the hiring process in India,
or even they couldn't help her
for the promotion from assistant professor
to associate professor
or even really promotions.
This experience
led her to shift her focus on publishing
her research in index to journals,
which also culminated into her
collaboration with Samya students.
And Zara is we to launch a special issue
dedicated to Indian electronic literature
and digital cultures.
Samya will elaborate on this later.
Can you move this right?
Yeah.
Talk about your work.
Thank you. Yes.
So to talk about my experience,
I published my first research paper
in collaboration with children and Doctor
Chandan
in the same special issue edited by Samya
and rotation period.
I have also published a review of dinner
and Stone Moves in Electronic Book Review,
along with an interview
with Dina Larsen in the same journal.
Dina Larsen, Doctor Shanmugam,
Priya and I are now developing
a special feature for Hyper Risk
based on our ongoing interview
series with scholars and practitioners
from non-English
electronic literature communities.
We are planning to publish
that special feature in
in the spring 2027 issue.
These experiences have given me
opportunity to participate in the field.
At the same time,
they have also brought me face to face
with some serious question
about academic publishing,
which I will discuss
later in my discussion.
Some can we move forward
and can you talk about the special issue?
Yes. So this is the special issue
that I was talking about.
And the workshop that we did
for this special issue was a workshop
just like this one.
Now you see it
published in front of your eyes
with all of the papers out there.
But the discussion for this special issue
that has come out
just now, you can see the introduction
and all the other papers.
We have eight papers.
It is a mammoth double special issue.
It also started in the year 2024,
first with the unconference,
which was also supported
by the likes of New Media Writing Prize
and and other people.
I think Doctor Liles
kinds is in the room.
My shout out and salute to them
if they are, if they are here.
It started over there.
The first iteration of the workshop
was there, and the second iteration
was yellow 2024, once again hosted by
the familiar
faces that we see in the room.
So this is exactly cut
to chase two years later,
and the entire special issue is out.
But it is not.
A linear journey, is
what I want to point out, because
when I was looking at journals
and approaching them
to publish my special issue,
there has been multiple journals
that has not even responded.
And I still remember that
I was having a conversation
and I was crying and screaming about it
like I am doing right now in a session
that was hosted by Dina Larsen.
Right.
Dina Larsen, the powerhouse,
I must say, and also one of my mentors.
Right.
And at that meeting, there happened to be
Mark Bernstein from Eastgate Systems.
And Mark being extremely kind alongside
Dina said that you can approach Journal
of New Review of Hypermedia
and Multimedia, and I did, and I was very,
very fortunate to have a space
in this particular journal right now.
My point is that this work cannot stop.
We must carry the momentum forward,
especially since we have a very tight
knit,
international, diverse community like that
we have cultivated across the years,
and it should be a launchpad
to build from here.
And that is my only call to action,
that this is a thing
that I still remember.
Yellow 2023 Town Hall in Queenborough
in the San Francisco Auditorium.
For those of you
who were there, you were there
is that I had a long conversation
about Scopus indexing.
I still remember Professor
Anand was there, professor
he was there, and we were having
a long conversation about,
is it very important for us
to go to indexing or to resist indexing?
My idea is we need both at the same time.
We need voices to emerge,
and we need these avenues in these places.
And at the same time, we need people
to break these systems of power as well.
Like as you see, that is also publishing
in these journals and also
writing critical responses
for the next, for that matter.
So it is a curious balance of both.
But at the same time, in order
to do these things, we need networks.
We need privileges of knowing people,
knowing what to do, knowing where to go.
And the idea here is that because I
myself
have been nurtured by this community.
Yellow.
When I started, I was a master's student
and now I'm a faculty.
Along the entire way,
I have been nurtured by this community,
and now I'm very moved with my colleagues
to take this forward
into the next possible step.
Would you like to talk
about the challenges?
Yeah.
So before we go further
to the challenges, I want to discuss
my personal experience here,
which I consider it as challenge.
So as highlighted by Samya
and many other
scholars,
I have faced one persistent dilemma
ever since I began my journey
in electronic literature in India.
So the question which should I publish
my research paper in Scopus?
Index to journal?
Or should I publish them in journals
such as Electronic Encryption,
which is one of the oldest open
access journals
and one of the most prominent journals
dedicated to the field of electronic
publishing.
In Electronic Review
would give my research
visibility among scholars
who are directly working in the field.
I would naturally prefer to publish
my research in an open access journal,
because such journal would make
my research more widely available.
However, as per my understanding,
many of these journals
are not indexed in Scopus or Science.
The institution where I am pursuing
my research has established
a qualification benchmark
requiring a certain number
of indexed publications
before I can receive my doctoral degree.
Therefore, even though I would like
to publish my research in prominent open
access journals dedicated to the field,
I am also required to publish
research articles in index
in order to complete my degree work.
I have repeatedly asked
many prominent scholars in the field
why Electronic Review is not indexed yet,
particularly when it has published
many prominent research
articles and groundbreaking works.
There must be some reasons for this,
and I am not in a position to judge
those reasons.
I also do not think that we should take
this discussion in that direction.
However, I would like to draw everyone's
attention to one serious concerns
that we encountered
during the publication process.
So when Doctor Shanmugam and I
were looking for a journal
to submit a paper on electronic literature
in Indian context,
we found a journal in which many prominent
electronic literature scholars,
including and Katherine
Haynes, had published research
on electronic literature
because the journal had previously
published work in this field.
We believed that our paper
with element to its scope.
We submitted the paper.
Unfortunately, after approximately one
and a half month, the journal returned it
with a desk rejection.
The only reason provided was that article
did not fit within general scope.
We asked for a more specific explanation
why the journal would not provide funding.
We then submitted the same paper
to one of the most prominent journals
in digital humanities.
We hope that the journal
will consider our people
because it had also previously published
many important research
articles on electronic literature.
However,
after waiting for more than two months,
we once again received a desk rejection.
The journal gave us the same week.
Explanation.
The paper did not fit within its core.
It also stated that the journal
was receiving a high number of submissions
and therefore would not include the paper.
Finally, the paper found a safe place
and is now in the review process
currently.
What I would like to highlight
through this experience is that a scholar
from countries such as India,
who wishes to pursue a career in emerging
and experimental field, such as electronic
literature, faces multiple challenges.
The difficulty begins
with finding an appropriate journal.
They continue through repeated rejections,
multiple revisions, long
waiting periods, and uncertainty
throughout the publication process.
In many cases, the complete process
of publishing a single article
inside
journals can take between 18 to 24 months.
Yes. Would you like to?
Yes. Of course.
And I would just like to highlight the
questions of authorship and collaboration.
Because even though we are saying
that we pulled off a special issue,
something like that,
it is not a 1 or 2 persons job,
especially
when all of them are early careers.
Because it was myself.
It was Doctor Shanmugam, Priya.
It is Doctor Zahira Rizvi
who I believe is watching
from the center for Digital Narrative,
where she is currently a postdoc.
So my wave and of course
last but not the least,
Professor Astrid Insulin.
Because we not only needed
to build a team,
but also we needed to build a team
with diverse experiences and career stages
who could contribute that
various expertise in pulling this through.
Because not only had a specialty shown,
electronic literature
specifically in India,
had never been done before.
It is also a task
to convince journal editors
because in the special issue
form, the editors ask you
for your prior experience of editors
editorship.
Now there are two problems a
for a early career scholar, a PhD scholar,
or anybody who's about to begin
their journey of scholarship.
How do you have your experience?
Everybody starts somewhere, right?
So for that, you need the mentorship
of senior scholars, number one.
And number two,
when you go to literary studies journals
and you say that you want to publish
electronic literature.
They say, no, this is not literature.
Go to media
studies, go to digital humanities.
We go to media studies Journal.
They'll say that this is not media
studies. This is narrative.
Go to literature journals.
Go to digital humanities journals.
How many digital humanities journals
do you think there are which are indexed
and which publishes
the some of the most famous ones
would be digital humanities
and digital scholarship in the humanities.
Imagine the amount of pressure
that they have in order to keep up
with the demands of publication.
So not everybody can publish
in those spaces within the given timeline,
which is why our method is to dissenter.
Our method is to build
the teams on our own right, gather voices
and start teaching, gathering our teams
and taking it somewhere with hope.
See where it can come through.
So yeah,
these are the ways out.
That's what we have been talking this far.
And thank you for being with me as well.
So this is a working document
that we have.
And this document has been live
since 2024, by the way,
if you just scan it, I hope it works.
If not, please let me know.
I'll put the link in the chat.
You will see that
the thought processes are still there
in this document from two years ago.
And I invite you in a separate tab
to comment your thoughts on
what kind of work you want to present,
what kind of work you want to do
so that we can get our heads together
and brainstorm something.
Not right
now. Maybe this will be a launchpad.
Maybe this will be a gathering space.
Last time,
our agenda was particularly clear
that we want to do a special issue
about India.
Now it can branch out,
it can be about the global South.
It can be about transnational cultures,
digital cultures,
electronic literature
across space and time.
But I invite you to think
I invite you to brainstorm.
Let's see where we can take it from here.
Yeah, I will put the link in the chat.
But for for the time being.
Yeah.
Just give me one moment.
I'll put the link in the chat. Oh.
Yeah.
I think you have already done it.
Yeah. Thank you so much.
Thank you.
Do you have editorial access
to this document?
It might be view only.
From what I can tell.
It might be view only. So just.
Just give me one moment.
So yeah, I have given
everybody editor access.
You see that
there are two tabs for 2024 and 2026.
So you can take a look at the discussions
that happened in 2024.
And you can go into the 2026 tab
and start putting in your thoughts
what you want to do.
Where do you want to see this
grow as a collective?
How can we do together?
How can we get our heads together
and do something productive
with the force that we have
in this room beyond wherever?
Yeah.
So for the time being, we can stop sharing
and maybe
we'll come back to our
thank you slide at the end.
And now let's get our heads together,
write something or discuss amongst
each others.
Others can also speak
and we can hear from others
about their publication experiences
and so on.
Is it okay if I stop sharing?
Yeah, yeah.
So can I add one point?
Like. Yes of course.
Optimistic feature future.
I think we need a new journal dedicated
specifically to literature
and writing practices
established by prominent scholars.
The journals would also work towards
being becoming indexed
because such a journal could support
and strength scholars
working in electronic literature
in countries such as India.
Because for many scholars, I would say
indexed publication, not simply
a matter of resting, it is a requirement
for entry and remaining within a calendar.
Without such opportunity,
some scholars may eventually be compelled
to shift toward adjacent dominant fields
or more conventional areas of research
in order to secure their careers.
So that can be a way to start.
I mean, create a new journal or else
why can't we make electronic book review?
I do amount of labor that goes behind.
Managing journals are tremendous because I
am associated with the Electronic Book
Review as one of the production editors,
and I see Teagan in the room as well.
The amount of labor
that goes in towards high tech.
Yeah.
And the amount of labor that goes in, in
just in the back
end of maintaining
journals is absolutely insane.
And because a field in a particular area
is dominated by people
who are early careers PhD scholars,
I think labor is hard to come by.
While having a journal
is a brilliant idea,
but it is difficult to sustain labor,
especially
because we need to create issue after one
after another.
I agree with you that a journal
has to be a way forward where we
we have other approaches
to make, etc., etc.
other contributions.
But yeah, for for now
we can look into spaces where we can
publish and later
we can definitely take inspiration
from the like of ever and hyper is
and have something of our own.
Definitely begun. You have a hand raised.
Hello.
Sorry, I just need to jump in
because I do know the reasoning behind
why it's not Scopus archived.
And that's because Electronic Book Review
started out publishing experimentally,
and we still do have quite a few articles
that don't actually meet
rigorous academic criteria,
but do allow for creative expression.
So if we start doing the Scopus way,
then we'll have to stop these different
avenues from being published.
So we're trying to bring IBA
into the future by making
sure it's Google Scholar Index
that we have doing that,
the archival content is being updated
and brought into the future,
but because of the experimental nature
of the journal, we're kind of constrained.
Our hands are tied.
So we either have to make this choice of
going Scopus and losing huge sides
of electronic book reviewers.
It exists or we retain it.
And then we have this issue,
which I completely understand
because I'm an emerging scholar as well.
It's it's frustrating, but I just wanted
to explain what's going on there.
Absolutely.
And I completely agree with you, Teigen.
And not just that the other method
should be that not everything
should be indexed
to these extremely powerful
and wealthy platforms,
because we should not ascribe
to one particular model of understanding
that this is what accounts
for a publication
and something that does not.
So yeah.
A special issue out with Stuart.
Can you talk a little bit
about that process of like how a project
like that comes together?
So that was with a predatory journal.
I mean, it's
well known to be a predatory journal.
The MGP journals are all like that.
But part of why Stuart did it
is because it is difficult
to get special issues of that type
where you have full editorial control,
and so the journals
will approach scholars
and they approach Stuart
kind of based on reputation,
and offer to have it
so that anyone you invite to be in
special issue
doesn't have to pay
the predatory article fee.
So none of us paid to publish there.
And so it's like it's kind of designed
so that you can do that type of
journal really easily, but it's really
a later career move because there are
lots of people who will judge you for even
having that type of journal on your CV.
So that's not something I would recommend
grad students get anywhere close to,
or early career or tenure track scholars,
because there's a lot of judgment
in the academic world, as has been
discussed here about where you publish.
Yeah,
yeah.
So just to take it away a little bit,
extend it from doctor anesthesia.
Comment I have applied
for academic positions around the world,
and one of the responses that I got
from a position that I did not get,
I completely understand competition
in the academic market.
And all of that is that the avenues
of publication
are more prestigious than others.
I mean, how do you determine,
do you boil everything down
to an impact factor,
and how do you assess these things?
Because because they are not symmetric.
They are they are unequal.
And historically disadvantaged
people are not likely
to have access to these spaces.
It's one of those days where
I want to go back to just doing creative
writing and having a chat book out with
like a print indie press or something.
I like to jump in. Mark, if you haven't.
Space creative writing.
Like, do you have some thoughts
that you want to unmute yourself
and share?
Everyone can see the words that I say
no, I think this is a great effort.
I mean, we've talked
kind of we talked ourselves in circles,
I think, and I appreciate Teigen's
perspective and insight into
these are kind of known issues
that we've as a community,
we've been trying to address for a while.
In addition to some of the
and I will say that in addition
to some of those
structural barriers,
perhaps there are still in our community
some cultural barriers
in terms of disciplinary studies
and what we expect of research,
what we how we're graded on research.
So there are different expectations
in different institutional settings.
So what is great for American
academics is not necessarily
the same as what's great for UK academics
or Indian academics or Australian.
And so for for example,
while I recognize how important
is to the community,
culturally it hasn't been accepting of
at least historically wasn't
accepting of practice based work.
It's gotten better, but it hasn't
been accepting of practice based work.
And then because
of those structural issues, it hasn't
it hasn't been a priority for like
British based scholars
who need need to have dois
who need to have it turn up
in, in the searches, that sort of thing.
So it's getting there.
But historically that
that's sort of a problem.
So these are things
that we need to think about
is don't ask me that question, Mark.
That's me.
When, when when you're asked
this is when you're told
this paper is awesome,
but you did it with your own work.
Can you do it with someone else's?
That's
not the journal for you at that time.
So,
so yeah.
Yeah it is. It was giving Wikipedia.
So there have been great changes
in the last decade with ever.
But again, some of the
then there's the contextual things
to think about in terms of, you know,
does this look as great for me
as a monograph?
Does this look as great for me
as something in this journal?
Yeah.
So, so it's a little bit of strategy.
And I,
I was also putting on the document
that we lost a really crucial journal
this year,
which is one of my favorite journals,
in which I went to over and over.
And because it was so open
and because it was welcoming
to lots of different types
of media research and lots of different,
it was really it was really, really
welcoming to early career researchers.
And their initial forays into.
First Monday is gone.
Yeah, first Monday I think
it will be archived, but it's gone.
And there was a group of us who queried
as to whether we could take it over
and continue it,
and the originating editors
editorial board said
there were reasons, like there was a
field of gossip that I was not privy to,
but there were
personal, professional reasons
why they didn't want it to continue.
So that effort is that was
that was just kind of cut off.
So first Monday gone.
But it does mean there's a gap there
that could be explored.
It it would need support.
I mean, there's always this issue of,
sure, you can throw something out there,
but I think PD can tell you with
with his experience with remediate,
how how much of a hill it is to climb to,
to sort of put out your shingle
and go from there.
And so
and I think that's one of the great things
about the group that you all have
is you do have a great group
and you're really motivated to do things.
I mean, you're already doing things
and creating new community
and new offshoots and new things,
and that's something
that we actually don't
have here in the UK.
We've got little pockets of us,
but there's we're having a little bit
of a generational effect right now
in that higher education in the UK is
being crapped on at every level.
Not quite as bad as the US,
but still not great.
I read an article this morning
that we have lost 4000
humanities jobs
in the last year in the UK,
so we're not a huge country,
so that's a pretty significant chunk.
And so that's so higher
education is struggling and humanities
in particular is struggling.
Just entire departments and and colleges
wiped out
in one fell of the sword
at many universities.
So this is kind of what we're facing.
We a lot of a lot of the scholars are
choosing to retire instead of continuing.
But when you're you've got
that sort of burgeoning field
that's happening and you can really start
to forge your own way.
I think that's really exciting.
And I think those of us
who are stuck a little bit
in, you know, in those environments,
I think it's exciting for us.
And we want to help as much as we can,
knowing that
in our own context
where handcuffed a little bit.
So I think
what I'm seeing is
that we will happily support,
contribute, edit review
ID eight, spread the news, etc.
as a community.
But a lot of us are in situations
where we're just glad
we have jobs day to day
and can pay our rent at the moment,
and don't know that that's
going to be the same case next year.
So yeah, so
that was a lot.
This is what happens
when you get Lyle to unmute.
And I kept it clean.
It's it's PG and mostly and.
Yeah I mean it depends on what
what different things are.
Yeah.
Mark, depending on your contract,
the research might not count.
My university might be they might decide
to go be a teaching university
in the end as well.
These things are it's
all lots of different machinations
and different things like that.
So I would say as if you're a group
that is burning with desire
to do things, to get something rolling.
Yes, listen to the community,
see what works for the community.
But first off, do what works for you.
What would help your group,
the core group that is doing it.
And then the second tier desires are what?
How can you get everyone else
involved and contributing?
Because in the end,
if if we could do these sorts of things,
we might be, but we can't.
And so it's really
about fulfilling your needs.
If that helps.
Yeah. Thank you.
Thank you very much.
That is amazing.
So and thank you, Mark, for
for agreeing to help out.
I think, I think that that means a lot
to us in the broader community.
So Mark,
your special issue with CLC review
was one of the earliest special issues
in a journal
that I could find on electronic literature
other than ever.
That was done in somewhere around 2016,
if I am not wrong. So.
So we would
you like to reflect on your journey and
the status of publishing
electronic literature since May?
You had a hand raised.
You want to jump in?
Mark?
Perhaps?
Yeah, I'm happy
to reflect in my current state.
Yeah.
So you know, but one of our coeditors,
I think I should give more of the
credit towards or both Coeditors
leading the charge in that
because they were institutions
that needed index publications for that.
But actually TLC web
was extremely welcoming to us as,
as a publication and gave us relatively
free reign with those articles.
So I would say.
I don't know.
My experience, I guess, is that
those journals are out there
where people are are more understanding.
I mean, it's such a strange equation
to just to even think about, right,
is that, you know, these
these journals need content to be produced
for free for them,
and then they need people to do free labor
for them to organize those special issues.
And again, we just finished doing
two special issues for digital humanities,
Humanities Quarterly.
And I would I would recommend continuing
to approach them with the idea
of like again.
They've been extremely supportive
and welcoming almost to degree.
That has been with when Jeremy
and I pitched our special issues
of Critical studies.
So I think just one thing to remember too,
is that when you like with a special issue
pitch, you're doing the journal a favor,
like you're you're taking you're taking
months, years of labor off of their hands.
And,
and I love what Lyle says, though, about
you need
to teach the world what's important
and what what scholarship needs
to be done.
And part of that self self-organizing,
rather than submitting to
is one of
is a strategy that I found tends to work
a little bit better.
I was thinking about that.
That presentation I saw yesterday by I'm
going to get the letters wrong DLP plus,
I don't know
if I've said the right letters,
but they were a small group of scholars
not like you, not unlike you
and my whole who, you know, started
having like many conferences
and things like that and started.
Maybe this is another thing
just to offer is that
it's not an either or.
Right.
So one thing I found to be true
just in life, this last little friend
during bit that I'll do in a kind of
like early state waking up,
you publish things in
ever maybe they're smaller,
they're going to get out faster.
Okay, then that's a building block for
the next thing that you're going to write
out of the same kind of
get in a sense of like, oh,
I can only write about this material once,
or every article needs to be new.
No, that's nonsense.
You publish it,
you publish that, you get it out quickly.
Great.
It's going to get to a great audience.
Can be indexed in Google, take that same
material, develop it, keep developing.
Okay. Now
that's going to turn into this article.
That's going to go somewhere else. Okay.
And then that then those people
you connect with in that moment
and through presenting that material
that's going to become the special issue.
Okay. Well then that thing is going
to become the book proposal.
Okay. Well,
you know what I mean. So it's like
my experience is if you can
somewhat free yourself from the numbers
quest of the metrics
in the developmental stages,
and you just focus on exactly
what you're doing,
community building and building,
getting those pieces in place,
getting those scholars
lined up that you like to work
with, that you know how to work with,
that are good,
that are good to work with okay.
Find the venues that are and really get
that sense of venues in their rhythms.
Right. Ebba publishes quickly.
DQ takes a bit longer to
you know, some journals are really hands
on, some of them are.
And also watch out for conferences
like ello
that has proceedings and I kids, I'm
going to put a petition for them
that always publishes their proceedings
because they're more computer science
sort of directed.
Anyway, once you get into that rhythm,
which is again
just takes sitting in the sea
for a little while, but
but most importantly,
I would say you guys are exactly on track
of where you need to be
because you've got important content,
you've got a burgeoning group of scholars,
you're building your network,
building your community.
And I know that all of us will
would be happy to lend our support.
And, you know, like, again,
there's something Noah said.
The other maybe no words
or Fruin said 5 or 10 years ago,
he stood up at a conference and said, I'm
now at the point where I can lend
my name to things
and help people in that way, right?
And I'm
ten years, 20 years from now,
maybe I'll be able to say such a thing
and the way no Bruin could say it, but but
again, I know a lot of us here at ello.
We love and support you guys.
And we're we're happy to lend whatever
our quote unquote name can offer,
you know, in terms
of giving this so-called gravitas,
I know all of us are more than happy
to to help out in that, that capacity.
But yeah.
So anyway, you guys are
you guys are exactly on track.
Yeah.
Thank you so much.
I know Mayhew is facing some bandwidth
issues, so that's perfectly fine.
We have had a significant amount
of critical mass
also in the document as well.
Some ideas, some conversations.
And we have about roughly 14 minutes left.
So if you want any any more thoughts
and things like that and reviews in speed
I completely agree.
Fantastic space about reviewing projects.
We recently did a project
about a special issue
about electronic literature
in reviews in Digital Humanities.
Please check it out.
It's it's fun
and there are some fun stuff.
So so yeah.
And if anyone else wants to say something
that how you want to join hands
or something of that sort.
Please do so. Yeah. Go on.
I agree
what professor and professor said,
but actually recently
I had a written experience
when I submitted my proposal to one of
I mean and Hope conference.
So one of the reviewers there said that
what electronic literature paper
or abstract doing in a conference.
So from there I got an idea
that why are we not getting recognized,
even if we have a multiple
feature and experimental nature?
And that's how we recently submitted.
That culminated
into special interest group proposal
that we recently submitted to.
And and we are waiting
for their suggestions.
If things work out,
we are planning to get electronically
on board to at home
with mini conferences with special issue.
And when you got community
building activities over there,
that may help us
getting recognized for their.
Yeah, absolutely.
Thank thank thank you so much.
Just to collaborate,
I also was talking about the state
of electronic literature
in Indian higher education
and submitted it
to a particular conference.
And one of the peer review comments
that I get
was this contributes
nothing new to the discipline.
So that is the work
of of a feeling the country
few careers summed up in one line.
So I mean interesting is
how I would like to react,
but let's not dwell into that.
We all have our experiences
and that would be a different
therapy session altogether.
But just to hear from the broader room
and there's always a review.
Yeah.
So if anybody would like to come in
and say a few words
or talk about this workshopping process
basically, which is less of a workshop,
more of a launchpad to to gather our heads
together to do something.
I see Professor Joe Tabby here, others.
So so if anyone would like to come in or
even joke if you'd like to say something,
it's always good to see you.
Or we
can just chill and run down the clock.
I can add it just a few sites
on kind of thinking outside the box
and where you're publishing right now,
because there are so many general
humanities spaces and humanities fields
that are trying to reckon
with generative AI,
and they don't know how to do it right.
That was kind of part
of what really came out in the keynote
yesterday is the folks who see the word
AI and assume certain things
about how creative
writing is being taught.
And there's a lot of
there are a lot of your colleagues
are kind of
potential colleagues and people
who are trying to recognize these things.
You do not have the depth of knowledge
and generative texts
that you bring from a practice
like electronic literature.
So at this moment,
there's there's always these trends
and higher education of something
that everyone's trying to publish
special issues on and get a grip on.
And right now, generative and key remains
one of those opportunities. So
there's both value.
If you're going kind of on the job market
to having some visibility on a topic
like that, because signals departments
that you can help them reckon
with those questions, but it's also just
pragmatically an opportunity
to go into spaces that don't normally talk
about electronic literature and say,
look, perhaps you'd like to reckon
with this history and how you're framing
generative text as slop
might not necessarily be most meaningful.
Like one of my grad students
and I published over in this journal,
book 2.0, which positions itself
as being about a more kind
of modern approach to publishing,
but has not really been a place
that much electronic literature content.
And we use AI kind of gateway to do it.
So as you're thinking about
how you can finish yourself and your work
and publish outside of these spaces
that have traditionally been
at least more friendly
to electronic literature,
there are opportunities
in like this to branch out.
Yep, yep.
And the more
that we write
and the more that we send things
to these journals,
the more that they start to see them
as acceptable and relevant
and all that sort of thing.
And I will say that anyone who is
submitting to.
How do I frame this
Western ecologies of thought
and disciplinary contexts?
Just be aware that any time
you are very clearly speaking
from a global majority frame of reference
and about global majority experiences,
you will get the sort of.
This adds nothing new to the discipline.
Or why are we still talking about this?
This is, you know,
or this is just a rant from someone
or this is the
you just have to.
Okay, gotcha.
You don't want to hear any more
about people who don't look like you.
Great. Next reviewer.
And it blows.
And hopefully the more that we push
and the more
that we get more wider, diverse people,
diversity of people,
the better it will get.
But we're not there yet.
So, yeah, we're it's it's
still coming along.
Yeah.
And one of the other languages
that they use is that
this particular argument does not suit
the scope of our journals,
because it does not refer
to the conversations
that are central
to our disciplinary understanding.
Just to give you a translation,
that means you are not citing our friends.
Yep. That is exactly right.
I have literally been in review fights
with reviewers
who are mad at someone
for refuting something that they wrote.
When they wrote something about that
person's community
and clearly didn't understand it,
you know, that sort of thing.
So, yeah, that kind of stuff
happens behind the scenes
and you just go, I mean, luckily
we're all creative writers,
and so we are used to rejection
and we just go, thank you.
Reviewer number two.
For me right now
it's reviewer number three.
And I will take this away with me
and go somewhere else
or I will repeat you in my
comments or whatever it is.
We all develop that tough skin,
although I think that many of us
don't appreciate how tough it has to be.
As you accept for figment
has no tough skin.
Figment is baby soft.
But you have to have
those gradations of tough skin
the further away
you get from the dominant hierarchy.
Sadly, but hopefully,
hopefully more of us doing it
and and screaming about it.
Y'all are making me
want to go get one of my chickens.
It would have to be Janeway because she's
the only one who likes cuddles.
But they escaped yesterday.
Yes. Excellent.
But yeah, just just keep swimming.
It's been interesting
to work on a larger
network graph of yellow.
I keep bringing it up
because I'm literally obsessed
and addicted to, like,
logging journals and publications
and people where they were published,
and to see which venues
really are like very near
to our cluster of research and to see
like what journals used
to be really close to our cluster
that have over time
published further away from us
just because of the way things
have changed since the 90s a lot of times.
But it's also an opportunity to like
I Mark,
I shared that the modernism conference,
I was just out with Leo
and Lyle and Monique and Jolene here,
but I am working to put
that can see if I can give you a it's
always it's always in front of me.
Unfortunately, there's never a day
where I don't have this up, but.
So there you are, Mark.
And it's you're you're very well connected
and very central
to what we're doing in ello.
But you'll see that like these journals
and edited collections and blogs, textiles
pretty near mat lit is really near to
what we're doing
ever is all over this internal map.
And then you have things like convergence
and neural.
And here's DK out here in the digital
humanities cluster, way out there
and has published a ton of us, and it's
also published a ton of other people.
So which is why it's further away.
But it's helped
me really get a sense for where the like,
if we're an interstitial interdisciplinary
field, like where what exactly where
in the borderlands up against and where
we might border cross a little bit.
There's always the persuasion
element of that.
But it is. It's exciting.
This is an obsidian Anjali.
I'm just
because Gaffey is too slow
and not as fun to work with.
The Wikileaks
structure is really exciting.
I would love for it to be published
somewhere.
Deakin I got
I got to draft something first.
It's in the works I have.
It is a, it's a GitHub repository though
that you could clone
and create a vault yourself
and like re-up date.
So I can put the link to that in the in
the chat.
It's always it's always in progress.
Yes. Jill did do
a network graph of yellow at one point,
I think through the dissertations
and through the citation networks
and the dissertations.
It's a great ever piece, I believe.
Yeah,
I think we can call it
quits because we we.
Left and a certain amount of discussions.
Thank you so much and Mehulkumar
for this discussion and for opening the,
the floor and the, the virtual space
for us to work together
on something with the doc.
Maybe we can find a way to get that linked
into our site or something like that.
But please everyone give a round of
applause to these presenters.